Thanks very much.
شكرًا جزيلاً لكم.
I am Hannah Fry, the badass.
أنا (هانا فراي)، الجريئة.
And today I'm asking the question:
واليوم أطرح هذا السؤال:
Is life really that complex?
هل الحياة حقًا معقدة لهذه الدرجة؟
Now, I've only got nine minutes to try and provide you with an answer,
عندي 9 دقائق فقط لأحاول أن أعطيكم إجابة،
so what I've done is split this neatly into two parts:
لذلك قسّمتها بعناية إلى جزئين:
part one: yes;
الجزء الأول: نعم،
and later on, part two: no.
ولاحقًا في الجزء الثاني: لا.
Or, to be more accurate: no?
أو، إذا أردنا الدقة: لا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So first of all, let me try and define what I mean by "complex."
أولاً، سأحاول أن أعرّف ما أقصدة بـ"معقدة".
Now, I could give you a host of formal definitions,
قد أعطيكم عددًا من التعريفات التقليدية،
but in the simplest terms,
لكن ببساطة،
any problem in complexity is something that Einstein and his peers can't do.
أي مشكلة معقدة هي شيء لا يقدر آينشتاين ورفاقه على حلّه.
So, let's imagine -- if the clicker works ... there we go.
فلنتخيل ... إذا اشتغل المؤشر ... ها هو.
Einstein is playing a game of snooker.
آينشتاين يلعب البلياردو.
He's a clever chap, so he knows that when he hits the cue ball,
إنه رجل ذكي ويعرف أنه عندما يضرب الكرة البيضاء
he could write you an equation
يمكن أن يكتب لك معادلة
and tell you exactly where the red ball is going to hit the sides,
تحدد أين ستضرب الكرة الحمراء الجوانب،
how fast it's going and where it's going to end up.
وكم سرعتها وأين سيكون موقعها الأخير.
Now, if you scale these snooker balls up to the size of the solar system,
إذا زدت مقياس تلك الكرات بحجم المجموعة الشمسية،
Einstein can still help you.
سيظل بمقدور آينشتاين مساعدتك.
Sure, the physics changes,
حتماً ستتغير الطبيعيات،
but if you wanted to know about the path of the Earth around the Sun,
لكن إذا أردت أن تعرف مسار الأرض حول الشمس،
Einstein could write you an equation
يمكن لآينشتاين أن يكتب لك معادلة
telling you where both objects are at any point in time.
تحدد موقع كلا الجسمين عند أي نقطة زمنية.
Now, with a surprising increase in difficulty,
وبزيادة مفاجئة في الصعوبة،
Einstein could include the Moon in his calculations.
يمكن لآينشتاين أن يضمّ القمر إلى حساباته.
But as you add more and more planets, Mars and Jupiter, say,
لكن كلما أضفت المزيد من الكواكب، مثل المريخ والمشترى،
the problem gets too tough for Einstein to solve with a pen and paper.
تزداد صعوبة المسألة وتتجاوز قدرة آينشتاين على حلها بورقة وقلم.
Now, strangely, if instead of having a handful of planets,
والعجيب أنه إذا استبدلت العدد المحدود من الكواكب
you had millions of objects or even billions,
بملايين الأجسام أو حتى مليارات منها،
the problem actually becomes much simpler,
تصبح المسألة أبسط بكثير،
and Einstein is back in the game.
ويعود آينشتاين إلى اللعبة.
Let me explain what I mean by this,
وسأفسر ما أقصده بذلك،
by scaling these objects back down to a molecular level.
بتخفيض مقياس تلك الأجسام إلى مستوى الجزيئات.
If you wanted to trace the erratic path of an individual air molecule,
إذا أردت تعقّب المسار المتذبذب لأحد جزيئات الهواء،
you'd have absolutely no hope.
فتلك حالة ميئوس منها.
But when you have millions of air molecules all together,
أما إذا كان لديك ملايين من جزيئات الهواء مجتمعة،
they start to act in a way which is quantifiable, predictable
فإنها تتحرك بطريقة قابلة للقياس والتوقع
and well-behaved.
وتعتبر منتظمة أيضًا.
And thank goodness air is well-behaved,
ولحسن الحظ أن الهواء منتظم الحركة،
because if it wasn't, planes would fall out of the sky.
فلو لم يكن كذلك، لسقطت الطائرات من السماء.
Now, on an even bigger scale, across the whole of the world,
وعلى مقياس أكبر، عبر أنحاء العالم،
the idea is exactly the same with all of these air molecules.
تظل الفكرة نفسها مع كافة جزيئات الهواء.
It's true that you can't take an individual rain droplet
صحيح أنه لا يمكنك تتبُّع قطرة مطر
and say where it's come from or where it's going to end up.
وتحديد من أين أتت وإلى أين ستتجه.
But you can say with pretty good certainty
لكنك تستطيع أن تحدد بدرجة جيدة من الدقة
whether it will be cloudy tomorrow.
إذا ما سيكون الطقس ضبابيًا غدًا أم لا.
So that's it.
هذا كل شيء إذًا.
In Einstein's time, this is how far science had got.
في أيام آينشتاين، كان هذا أقصى ما توصل إليه العلم.
We could do really small problems with a few objects
كنا قادرين على حل المسائل البسيطة التي تحتوي على القليل من الأجسام
with simple interactions,
وقدر بسيط من التفاعلات.
or we could do huge problems with millions of objects
أو كنا نحل المسائل الكبيرة التي تحتوي على ملايين الأجسام
and simple interactions.
وقدر بسيط من التفاعلات.
But what about everything in the middle?
لكن ماذا عن كل شيء في الوسط؟
Well, just seven years before Einstein's death,
قبل وفاة آينشتاين بسبع سنوات،
an American scientist called Warren Weaver made exactly this point.
طرح عالم أمريكي اسمه (وارن ويفر) تلك المسألة بالتحديد.
He said that scientific methodology has gone from one extreme to another,
قال أن منهجية البحث العلمي قد عالجت المسائل الصغيرة والكبيرة،
leaving out an untouched great middle region.
بدون التطرق للمنطقة الشاسعة التي تتوسطها.
Now, this middle region is where complexity science lies,
وفي تلك المنطقة الوسطى يأتي دور علوم المسائل المعقدة،
and this is what I mean by complex.
وهذا ما أقصده بالتعقيد.
Now, unfortunately, almost every single problem you can think of
وللأسف، تقريباً تقع كل المسائل التي يمكنك التفكير فيها
to do with human behavior
والمتعلقة بالسلوك البشري
lies in this middle region.
في تلك المنطقة الوسطى.
Einstein's got absolutely no idea how to model the movement of a crowd.
لا يدري آينشتاين كيف يضع نموذجًا لحركة الحشود.
There are too many people to look at them all individually
فعدد الناس كبير ويحول دون تتبع كل منهم على حدة
and too few to treat them as a gas.
وهو صغير لذا لا يمكن معاملتهم مثل الغازات.
Similarly, people are prone to annoying things like decisions
كما يميل الناس للقيام بأشياء مزعجة مثل اتخاذ القرارات
and not wanting to walk into each other,
وتجنب الاصطدام ببعضهم البعض،
which makes the problem all the more complicated.
مما يجعل المشكلة أكثر تعقيدًا.
Einstein also couldn't tell you
ولا يستطيع آينشتاين أيضًا أن يخبرك
when the next stock market crash is going to be.
متى سيحدث الانهيار التالي لسوق الأسهم.
Einstein couldn't tell you how to improve unemployment.
ولا يستطيع أن يخبرك كيف تعالج البطالة.
Einstein can't even tell you
ولا يستطيع حتى أن يخبرك
whether the next iPhone is going to be a hit or a flop.
إذا ما كان هاتف آيفون التالي سينجح أم سيخفق.
So to conclude part one: we're completely screwed.
إذاً نستنتج من الجزء الأول أننا سنفشل فشلًا ذريعًا.
We've got no tools to deal with this, and life is way too complex.
وليست لدينا أدوات للتعامل مع الأمر وأن الحياة معقدة للغاية.
But maybe there's hope,
لكن قد يكون هناك أمل،
because in the last few years,
لأنه وفي الأعوام القليلة الأخيرة،
we've begun to see the beginnings of a new area of science
شهدنا بدايات مجال جديد من العلوم
using mathematics to model our social systems.
يعتمد على الرياضيات لوضع نماذج لأنظمتنا الاجتماعية.
And I'm not just talking here about statistics and computer simulations.
ولا أقصد الإحصاء والمحاكاة الحاسوبية فحسب.
I'm talking about writing down equations about our society
بل أقصد كتابة معادلات عن مجتمعنا
that will help us understand what's going on
ستساعدنا في فهم ما يجري حولنا
in the same way as with the snooker balls or the weather prediction.
بنفس أسلوب توقع كرات البلياردو أو التنبؤ بالطقس.
And this has come about because people have begun to realize
وقد حدث ذلك لأن الناس بدأوا يدركون
that we can use and exploit analogies
أنه يمكننا الاستفادة من المقارانات
between our human systems and those of the physical world around us.
بين الأنظمة البشرية والطبيعية من حولنا.
Now, to give you an example:
على سبيل المثال:
the incredibly complex problem of migration across Europe.
الهجرة عبر أنحاء أوروبا، والتي تعتبر مشكلة معقدة للغاية.
Actually, as it turns out, when you view all of the people together,
في الواقع، اتضح أنك عندما تنظر إلى كل الحشود البشرية،
collectively, they behave as though they're following the laws of gravity.
ستجد أنها تتصرف مجتمعةً وكأنها تتبع قواعد الجاذبية.
But instead of planets being attracted to one another,
لكن في هذه الحالة، بدلًا من انجذاب الكواكب لبعضها البعض،
it's people who are attracted to areas with better job opportunities,
فإن البشر هم من ينجذبون نحو المناطق التي بها فرص وظيفية أفضل
higher pay, better quality of life and lower unemployment.
وأجور أعلى وجودة حياة أفضل وبطالة أقل.
And in the same way as people are more likely to go for opportunities
وبنفس الطريقة التي تجعل احتمال انجذاب الناس بشكل أكبر نحو الفرص
close to where they live already -- London to Kent, for example,
القريبة من محل إقامتهم، مثل (لندن) إلى (كنت)،
as opposed to London to Melbourne --
بدلاً من (لندن) إلى (ملبورن)،
the gravitational effect of planets far away is felt much less.
فإن تأثير جاذبية الكواكب البعيدة يكون منخفضًا جدًّا.
So, to give you another example:
لنأخذ مثالًا آخر:
in 2008, a group in UCLA were looking into the patterns
في 2008، بحثت مجموعة في جامعة كالفورنيا عن أنماط
of burglary hot spots in the city.
انتشار السرقة في المدينة.
Now, one thing about burglaries is this idea of repeat victimization.
وأحد الأنماط المتعلقة بالسرقات هي معاودة الإيذاء.
So if you have a group of burglars who manage to successfully rob an area,
فإذا نجحت مجموعة من الجناة في سرقة منطقة ما،
they'll tend to return to that area and carry on burgling it.
فإنهم يميلون للعودة إلى تلك المنطقة والاستمرار في سرقتها.
So they learn the layout of the houses,
فهم يتعرفون على أوصاف المنازل
the escape routes
وطرق الهروب
and the local security measures that are in place.
والاحتياطات الأمنية القائمة.
And this will continue to happen
وسيظل ذلك يحدث
until local residents and police ramp up the security,
حتى يشدد السكان والشرطة التدابير الأمنية،
at which point, the burglars will move off elsewhere.
عندئذٍ، سينتقل السارقون إلى مكان آخر.
And it's that balance between burglars and security
والمعادلة بين السارقين والتدابير الأمنية
which creates these dynamic hot spots of the city.
تحدد مناطق انتشار السرقات في المدينة.
As it turns out, this is exactly the same process
وقد اتضح أن هذه نفس العملية
as how a leopard gets its spots,
التي تتوزع من خلالها نقاط النمر
except in the leopard example, it's not burglars and security,
لكن في حالة النمر لا تكون المعادلة بين السارقين والأمن،
it's the chemical process that creates these patterns
لكنها العملية الكيميائية التي تكوّن تلك الأنماط
and something called "morphogenesis."
وشيء اسمه "التشكّل الحيوي".
We actually know an awful lot about the morphogenesis of leopard spots.
إننا في الحقيقة نعرف الكثير جدًا عن التشكّل الحيوي لنقاط النمر.
Maybe we can use this to try and spot some of the warning signs with burglaries
ربما يمكننا الاستفادة من ذلك في محاولة تحديد بعض العلامات التحذيرية للسرقات
and perhaps, also to create better crime strategies to prevent crime.
وربما أيضًا نبتكر خططًا أمنية أفضل للحد من الجريمة.
There's a group here at UCL
وتوجد مجموعة هنا في كلية لندن
who are working with the West Midlands police right now
تعمل حاليًا مع شرطة ميلاند الغربية
on this very question.
على تلك المسألة تحديدًا.
I could give you plenty of examples like this,
يمكنني إعطاؤكم الكثير من الأمثلة كهذه،
but I wanted to leave you with one from my own research
لكن أريد أن أترككم مع مثال من أبحاثي
on the London riots.
عن أحداث شغب إنجلترا.
Now, you probably don't need me to tell you
وعلى الأرجح، لا حاجة لإخباركم
about the events of last summer,
عن أحداث الصيف الماضي،
where London and the UK saw the worst sustained period
حين شهدت لندن والمملكة المتحدة أسوء فترة متواصلة
of violent looting and arson
من أحداث السرقات والتخريب
for over twenty years.
على مدى عشرين عامًا.
It's understandable that, as a society, we want to try and understand
من المعقول أن نرغب كمجتمع محاولة فهم
exactly what caused these riots,
ما يسبب تلك الاضطرابات تحديدًا،
but also, perhaps, to equip our police with better strategies
وأن نرغب أيضًا في مدِّ شرطتنا بإعدادات أفضل
to lead to a swifter resolution in the future.
لكي يتم حسم الأمور بسرعة أكبر في المستقبل.
Now, I don't want to upset the sociologists here,
أنا لا أريد أن أضايق علماء الاجتماع هنا،
so I absolutely cannot talk about the individual motivations for a rioter,
لذلك، لن أتحدث عن الدوافع الفردية للمشاغب،
but when you look at the rioters all together,
لكن عندما تنظر للمشاغبين سويًا،
mathematically, you can separate it into a three-stage process
فمن الناحية الرياضية، يمكنك تجزئة الأمر إلى عملية من ثلاث مراحل
and draw analogies accordingly.
ثم عقد المقارنات وفقًا لذلك.
So, step one: let's say you've got a group of friends.
- الخطوة الأولى: لنفترض أن هناك مجموعة من الأصدقاء.
None of them are involved in the riots,
ولا أحد منهم تدخل في أعمال شغب،
but one of them walks past a Foot Locker which is being raided,
لكن أحدهم مر بجوار متجر أحذية يتعرض للسرقة
and goes in and bags himself a new pair of trainers.
فدخله وأخذ حذاءً جديدًا.
He texts one of his friends and says, "Come on down to the riots."
ثم أرسل لأحد أصدقائه قائلًا: "انضمّ معنا إلى الأحداث."
So his friend joins him,
فينضم إليه صديقه،
and then the two of them text more of their friends, who join them,
ثم يرسل كليهما للمزيد من الأصدقاء الذين ينضمون إليهما،
and text more of their friends
ويرسلون للمزيد من الأصدقاء
and more and more, and so it continues.
والمزيد والمزيد ويستمر الأمر هكذا.
This process is identical to the way that a virus spreads through a population.
هذه العملية مشابهة للطريقة التي ينتشر بها الفيروس بين الجموع.
If you think about the bird flu epidemic of a couple of years ago,
إذا فكرت في أمر وباء إنفلونزا الطيور الذي حدث منذ بضعة أعوام،
the more people that were infected, the more people that got infected,
كلما زاد عدد المصابين بالعدوى، زاد عدد المرضى
and the faster the virus spread
وزاد انتشار الفيروس
before the authorities managed to get a handle on events.
قبل تمكّن السُلطات من السيطرة على الأحداث.
And it's exactly the same process here.
وهذه نفس العملية التي تحدث هنا بالضبط.
So let's say you've got a rioter, he's decided he's going to riot.
فلنقُل أن هناك مشاغب، وقرر المشاركة في أعمال الشغب.
The next thing he has to do is pick a riot site.
ما سيفعله بعد ذلك هو اختيار موقع الشغب.
Now, what you should know about rioters is that, um ...
ما يجب أن تعرفوه عن المشاغبين هو أنهم...
Oops, clicker's gone. There we go.
ضاع المؤشر ... ها هو.
What you should know about rioters is, they're not prepared to travel
ما يجب أن تعرفوه عن المشاغبين هو أنهم ليسوا على استعداد للتنقل
that far from where they live,
إلى مسافات بعيدة عن منازلهم،
unless it's a really juicy riot site.
إلا إذا كان موقع الشغب جذابًا جدًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So you can see that here from this graph,
ويمكنكم أن تلاحظوا ذلك هنا على هذا الرسم البياني،
with an awful lot of rioters having traveled less than a kilometer
حيث أن عددًا كبيرًا جدًا من المشاغبين انتقلوا إلى مسافة أقل من كيلومتر
to the site that they went to.
نحو الموقع الذي اتجهوا إليه.
Now, this pattern is seen in consumer models of retail spending,
ويمكن ملاحظة هذا النمط في نماذج إنفاق المستهلكين في تجارة التجزئة،
i.e., where we choose to go shopping.
بمعنى، الأماكن التي نختار أن نتسوق فيها.
So, of course, people like to go to local shops,
بالطبع يفضل الناس الذهاب إلى المتاجر المحلية،
but you'd be prepared to go a little bit further
لكنهم على استعداد للذهاب إلى مكان أبعد قليلًا
if it was a really good retail site.
إذا كان موقع المتجر جيدًا جدًا،
And this analogy, actually, was already picked up by some of the papers,
وقد تم استخدام تلك المقارنة تحديدًا في بعض الصحف،
with some tabloid press calling the events "Shopping with violence,"
حيث كانت بعض عناوين الأحداث: "التسوق بعنف"،
which probably sums it up in terms of our research.
وهذا تقريبًا يلخص موضوع بحثنا.
Oh! -- we're going backwards.
آه... لقد عدنا للخلف.
OK, step three.
حسنًا، الخطوة الثالثة.
Finally, the rioter is at his site,
أخيرًا، وصل المشاغب إلى المكان،
and he wants to avoid getting caught by the police.
ويريد تجنب قبض الشرطة عليه.
The rioters will avoid the police at all times,
يتجنب المشاغبون الشرطة في كافة الأوقات،
but there is some safety in numbers.
لكن العدد الكبير يعطي إحساسًا بالأمان.
And on the flip side, the police, with their limited resources,
وعلى الجانب المقابل، فإن الشرطة، بإمكانياتها المحدودة،
are trying to protect as much of the city as possible,
تحاول حماية أكبر مساحة ممكنة من المدينة
arrest rioters wherever possible
واعتقال المشاغبين حيثما أمكن
and to create a deterrent effect.
وإحداث تأثير ردعي.
And actually, as it turns out,
وفي الحقيقة، كما اتضح لنا،
this mechanism between the two species, so to speak, of rioters and police,
تلك الآلية بين الفصيلتين، على سبيل المثال، أي المشاغبين والشرطة،
is identical to predators and prey in the wild.
مماثلة للكائنات المفترسة وفريستها في البرية.
So if you can imagine rabbits and foxes,
فإذا تخيلت الأرانب والثعالب،
rabbits are trying to avoid foxes at all costs,
تحاول الأرانب تجنب الثعالب بأي ثمن،
while foxes are patrolling the space, trying to look for rabbits.
بينما تجوب الثعالب المنطقة محاولةً البحث عن الأرانب.
We actually know an awful lot about the dynamics of predators and prey.
إننا في الحقيقة نعرف الكثير جدًا عن تحركات الكائنات المفترسة وفريستها.
We also know a lot about consumer spending flows.
كما أننا نعرف الكثير عن تسلسلات إنفاق المستهلكين،
And we know a lot about how viruses spread through a population.
وعن كيفية انتشار الفيروسات بين الجموع.
So if you take these three analogies together and exploit them,
فإذا جمعت تلك المقارنات الثلاث سويًا وقمت باستغلالها،
you can come up with a mathematical model of what actually happened,
يمكنك استنتاج نموذج رياضي لما حدث بالفعل،
that's capable of replicating the general patterns
وذلك النموذج قادر على تكرار الأنماط العامة
of the riots themselves.
لأحداث الشغب.
Now, once we've got this, we can almost use this as a petri dish
وعندما يكون ذلك النموذج بحوزتنا، يمكننا استخدامه كطبق بتري
and start having conversations
والبدأ في خوض محادثات
about which areas of the city were more susceptible than others
عن أنحاء المدينة التي تعرّضت للشغب أكثر من غيرها
and what police tactics could be used
وأي من الخطط الشُرطية يمكن استخدامها
if this were ever to happen again in the future.
إذا تكرر حدوث ذلك في المستقبل.
Even twenty years ago, modeling of this sort was completely unheard of.
حتى قبل 20 عامًا، لم تكن النماذج من هذا النوع شيئًا معروفًا.
But I think that these analogies are an incredibly important tool
لكن أظن أن تلك المقارنات هي أداة مهمة
in tackling problems with our society,
للتعامل مع المشكلات في مجتمعنا،
and perhaps, ultimately improving our society overall.
وربما، في النهاية، تحسين حالته العامة.
So, to conclude: life is complex,
ونستنتج من ذلك أن الحياة معقدة،
but perhaps understanding it need not necessarily be that complicated.
لكن لا داعي أن يكون فهمها معقدًا إلى تلك الدرجة.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)